pleased to welcome in now Yahoo Sports
NFL writer Charles McDonald who has one
of his mocks out. The guy's already up
to 7.0 on the mock draft. My goodness.
>> Talk about putting in the time.
>> Charles, where did you start? The day
after Christmas.
>> You're a goner, man.
>> Seven mocks.
>> Let's go. Th
>> This has actually become a running joke
in my friend group for the past couple
years. Uh you know, me and Nate Ty, we
do the mock drafts together over at
Yahoo. and uh we we you know I feel like
we're not the only people who might
write a mock or two during the season,
but we probably are the only people that
are still counting those mocks into the
off season. Uh so like seven one of
those is probably in October. So it's
not like we're we're doing this every
week. Not not yet.
>> Yeah. I mean I I'm I saw 7.0. I was
like, "Wow, where does that end?" 18 20
like You might hit a record here. Yeah.
Um, but let's let's dive into it because
I found your your pick for the Bills at
26 to be very interesting, especially in
light of the recent free agent
acquisitions, which you noted when you
made the pick of Emanuel McNeel Warren,
the safety out of Toledo for the Bills
at 26. You acknowledged, yeah, I know
they added Gino Stone. I know they added
CJ Gardner Johnson, but I'm picking this
guy for them anyway. What what prompted
you to go there when you could probably
make an argument for some other
defensive positions for the Bills?
>> Um, we actually Okay, that was actually
Nate's pick, but I know I feel the same
way uh as Nate because we we do like
even the odds in theirs, but uh I know I
know for that one because we did talk
about that one because I I found it
interesting. Uh, I think when you look
at the Bills secondary and and also I I
I would also say that pick is probably a
function of this draft and kind of how
like our mock draft fell. Um, because I
think I think this draft it gets kind of
it gets a little spooky around like pick
12 or 13 because I think there's there's
a big tier drop off and then there's
probably going to be a run on on edge
rushers at the top. So, you're looking
at guys who might not play like what you
think of as like val quote unquote
valuable positions. Like when you see
Caleb DS like not be a top two pick in
the draft even though he's one of the
best players in the in the country, it's
just because he plays safety. And I
think that uh uh Emanuel from Toledo, he
could be a guy that falls down the board
a little bit. I mean, I like his game,
but he's still like a classic kind of
like box safety. um you know, a big guy
uh that's going to hit and play uh play
down and like you know, play those flats
uh towards the sidelines and kind of be
that enforcer role. And Nate's reasoning
was uh you know, he's he's a a Wisconsin
guy goes back for a long time, been a a
gym letterer fanatic as long as I've
known him, which has been several years
now. Uh and he he thought that that was
just a good fit for his defense and
maybe a better fit than what uh some of
the players that Buffalo has. uh on
their unit and yeah they they did add
guys like you know CJ Garter Johnson but
that's just a stop gap. U we'll see what
happens with Cole Bishop this year. I
know he's probably looking to have a
better year this year than uh maybe he
did last year or a more consistent year
but they might not have like that big
safety enforcer role that uh you know
Nate says that uh uh Jim Leonard is a
big fan of.
>> Yeah. And one of the things about Jim
Leonard that they do put a lot on the
plate to the safeties and they need a
guy there that and with these Yeah. you
know, with the veterans they signed,
Gino Stone, CJ Gardner Johnson. They've
got some guys who've been around the
block and kind of are aware of what's
going to be on their plate. Um, gives a
young player a chance to get up ramped
up. But if you can get a guy in this
draft that you can, you know, foresee to
put a, you know, long future, get over
the club at a spot you need, that's,
yeah, whether you need it or not, you
may sign the guy and draft the guy in
that spot. Another guy that's mentioned
>> because Go ahead. about it. You might
you might not need him this year, but
you probably will next year, you know,
depending on on what moves you make or
guys you don't resign. And you know, we
we've seen like like the um like the
Eagles kind of incorporate strategies
like this, especially on the offensive
line where you know, Jason Kelsey, he's
got a few years left, but they still
draft Cam Jurgens and have him sit and
uh you know, kind of work him in in
there. So there there's a little bit of
a uh you know, we've already seen it
happen at other positions. So, I think
this would make sense and you can never
have enough DBs, especially when you're
talking about playing Drake May twice a
year.
>> Are you are you seeing around the league
team like because most fans are a little
bit less patient than that, right? You
got draft a guy in the first round, even
if it is a 26 pick, you kind of expect a
guy to plug in, right? Um, are more
teams
being more patient with guys outside the
position of quarterback?
>> Uh, no. I don't think so. Right. I I I I
I I feel like you're still just kind of
dropping guys in and seeing and seeing
who's the best and who can play uh for
the most part. I I I think it'd be
interesting to kind of kind of do stuff
like that. I I can think of a handful of
defensive linemen that could use like
just a sit here. Uh you look at like
where Shamar Stewart was for Cincinnati
last year and uh you know there are guys
who come in the league that aren't
ready, but I still think for the most
part you're you're just throwing these
guys to the wolves. It kind of I think
at other positions it kind of takes it
takes a little bit more to be able to
flex like that. Like when you look at
the Eagles and what they've been doing
on the offensive line, but yeah, it
helps when you've got Lane Johnson and
you've got Jason Kelce and uh you had uh
man the the the guard they had from uh
Houston uh man I can't remember his name
uh who they signed over Brandon Brooks
who was there and then they replaced him
and Landon Dickerson and you just kind
of keep this machine moving. But you you
have to have those good players that are
already there that can kind of hold the
fort down while guys get better, which
is a really tough thing to do. So I I I
think you're probably just going to see
teams just say, "All right, go out
there, especially with all these
receivers in the draft." Uh, you know,
one of these guys has got to be good. I
That'll be interesting spot to see how
that shakes out as well.
>> Charles, you mentioned that, you know,
there's going to be an edge rusher run
probably somewhere between 10 and 20.
>> Um,
>> yeah. you know, after, you know, the top
flight guy is off the board like Bailey.
Um, but how many realistically
fit in that range? Are we talking three,
four? I mean, we've seen the knock on
Cash Cashes Howell and his arm length.
Yeah. Um, there's a mixed bag of
perception on Armason Thomas, who some
people feel could go anywhere from 20 to
35. Um, so there seems to be in that
next tier a wide range of opinion, but
what level of surprise would you have if
the run on edge has like two spurts
somewhere in 10 to 20 there's a run, if
you will, and then maybe the next tier,
could it drop in where the Bills are at
26?
>> Yeah, I I I've I was honestly thinking
about that last week, that exact
question when we were doing our mock
draft. um uh last week. But what I would
say is I think I think there will be a
run after the first guys go off the
board because uh you know depending how
you look at him like you're you're
talking about Arll Reese, David Bailey,
Ruben Bane, those guys are obviously
going to be long gone before Buffalo
picks. Um and then you're you're kind of
in like like there's like a one and a
half tier maybe where you're looking at
guys like Kendrick Faulk if you look at
as an edge rusher or uh Keem Mesazor,
the other Miami edge. what what I've had
trouble figuring out is like who's the
who's the one that kind of starts that
second run because there there there's
so many different opinions about um this
defensive line class uh this year
because you know I'm someone who like I
like Zion Young from Missouri but I
don't know if I'll take him in the first
round. I've seen Malachai Lawrence from
UCF get hype. Uh TJ Parker from Clemson.
You talk about Casius how RMason Thomas.
Uh there there's there's a lot to choose
from it. And it's kind of like just pick
your style. Like what what do you need
for your defense? You might be re, you
know, quote unquote reaching a little
bit, but I'm not sure how many guys are
or how many teams are going to have all
that many first round grades. And we say
that every year, but I think this year
could be uh even a little bit worse when
you're just looking at strictly blue
chip talent at the top. Um not, you
know, we've got one quarterback. uh
you've got some tackles that are
probably going to come down maybe later
at the bottom of the top 10, but true
blue chip talents only going to be a
handful. So, it's really hard to peg
like who will be that guy. Like if
Buffalo decides that they want to take
an edge rusher at the bottom of the
first round, you know, there's choices
there. I'm not sure who they would pick,
but I I think who like who they decide
they would take would definitely show a
lot about their defense because uh like
I said, there's kind of a a little bit
of flavor for everybody in that second
edge group, I think. Well, we've seen,
you know, these the money positions, the
wide receivers, edge rushers, obviously
quarterback. Um, but the the spot and
you had the Bills taking a safety, which
is usually not a money spot uh for a
position. It's like wide receiver, edge,
quarterback. Talking about the Bills
also are looking for a standup off the
ball Mike linebacker, one of those guys
that can be the green dot on his helmet.
Um, and at 26
historically, you might be able to get a
really good one there. Uh, and you
mentioned CJ Allen in the mock as maybe
one of the other guys that would be
available at that spot. Um, is there
other guy other names we should watch
for if the Bills do go a different
direction?
>> Uh, I think if at linebacker you're at
at that point, you're probably looking
at two guys. Uh, because obviously like
Avar Reese will be gone, Sunonny Styles
will be long gone. Um, so I would say
you're looking at CJ Allen from Georgia
and then Anthony Hill from Texas. Um,
they're kind of like if you could put
CJ's brain in Anony's body, like that
would be a top five pick. Um, cuz CJ he
like he he is the green dot guy uh for
Georgia since he was a freshman. Like he
had he was so good as a freshman they
had to tell seniors to get off out of
here, go play at Kentucky for uh your
last year. like CSU had started for a
couple years uh and he locked down that
spot pretty pretty much immediately from
uh the time he was about 18. And I'm I'm
biased as a Georgia fan. Look, I'm I'm
going to say like I love this guy. Like
I I would give him almost single-handed
credit for the reason that as to why
they were able to beat Auburn this year.
Uh so so that's my guy. Um but he's not
not the fastest guy, you know, and I
think that that's probably why you'll
see him at uh maybe the bottom of the
first round. But it's not like he's he's
a total slouch athletically. he just
doesn't have like that high-end speed
maybe that makes you think uh this is
going to be an allp pro player in the
league. But uh just the smarts, the
physicality, the be ability to play
downhill and make tackles in space is
just a really really strong player. Um
and I think that this linebacker class
is is kind of interesting because when
you when you look at the league right
now, how many like elite offball
linebackers are there? Because you I I I
could make the case that there's one and
he broke his leg last year in Fred
Warner. um because Roan Smith hasn't
been the same uh for a couple years. So,
uh when you those were kind of the two
guys and we haven't had anyone young
kind of push their their way into that
sphere yet. Um but now I've been
thinking are these guys more valuable?
Uh because we we we kind of been taught
to think linebackers aren't valuable,
blah blah blah blah blah. But if no one
has an elite one and you have a chance
to get one, doesn't that make that a
little bit more valuable because you
have an asset no one else has? and we
see uh how good Fred is and how he can
choke the middle of the field and also
play the run. Like an elite guy still
changes your defense. Uh and the fact
that we have, you know, depend on how
again depending how you look at Arville
Ree, we could have four guys go in the
first round this year. That's uh kind of
a big change from where we've been
recently.
>> Yeah. And with respect to CJ Allen
specifically,
>> I would think in a three four defense,
which is what the Bills are switching
to,
>> there's less ground to cover if he's the
mic. um you know there and so you know
the gaps are fewer at the second level
and he can just go run and hit and and
largely stay inside the tackle box to a
great degree. Coverage might be a
different subject. Um it it almost seems
that his value would be higher for the
34 team like the Bills who are you know
moving to that scheme. Would you agree
with that? Yeah. And uh you know that's
uh that's what uh what what Kirby has.
You know Kirby's kind of evolved his
defense from more like when he was at
Alabama running a lot of like pure 34
and now at Georgia they run more like
tight stuff which is bad for defensive
linemen but it's good for for defending
those those crap offenses that you know
they throw out there every Saturday. Uh
but still like you're getting a lot of
like three to like fiveman surfaces
which is what you're looking at still in
a in a a three four defense. So like
visually it's kind of the same thing
from from a linebacker perspective. Uh
and Kirby, you know, that's passed down
from Sabin was passed down from
Belichic. So, you know, it's all part of
the same tree, which is why I think
you've seen, you know, uh, you know,
some of these Georgia defenders, they've
been, you know, able to to get going
during their rookie contracts the last
few years. Uh, you know, we just saw
Nicole Dean and Craig Walker get paid.
So,
>> uh, that's a that that's a that's a good
fit for them. I would love to see that
fit, you know, because it's just also
fun to think that Jim could get his
enforcer year one and get your green dot
guy. Someone who's had those
responsibilities for Kirby Smart's
defense for the past few years. It's a
really good fit. Um I guess like the
only the only thing maybe that put gives
you pause is is the range and coverage,
but you know, it's not so bad that like
I'm not considering as a first round
pick. You know, it it's adequate. It's
just not like you know, Sunonny Styles
running a 44 at 250 pounds. Like you
know, he's not that guy.
>> Right. Right. What are some the guys you
go down the list if you go from the
stand up linebacker back to the safety
position? You got these got a lot of
safeties at the combine impressed
because of the speed. I mean, you got
some bigger dudes running it like Thaman
Theamman uh ran from Oregon. He looks
like he'll still be on the board even if
uh the Bills are picking and they do
pick um the you know the guy you said
this Emanuel McNeel Warren.
How do you discern which guys are better
when you've got all these safeties at
the top of this draft who and some of
whom tested better than maybe they were
scouted before the combine?
>> Yeah, that was interesting. Um I
because I I've been youing through the
safety class and I don't really feel all
that different about these guys after
the combine. um you know is more like
sometimes you you see a combine number
you didn't expect and you got to take
another pass real quick. Okay, you know
maybe are you're a little you know more
athletic than I thought you were, but
you're still not making like the plays
that we want to see from an impact
safety. Um, and I and I I I think that
this class is it's going to be
interesting to see like where The
Endaman and Emanuel McNeel Warren go
because the bottom like once you get
past those guys personally personally
how I feel I I I just think it's just
it's just okay. You know, I'm not sure
if I see like too many uh long-term
starters here and that could be wrong,
but it feels like, you know, you got DS
who will, you know, unless you do like a
Julio Jones kind of trade, he's not
going to be a bill. the enderman is is
kind of where you get into that range of
where like I've heard he could go top
I've heard he could go like top 20 I've
heard top 40 so he's he could be there
at 26 and obviously uh Manny McNeil
Warren from Toledo is is probably going
to still be on the board in that range
but once you get past that you you're
you're probably taking a depth guy you
know some some people like like uh AJ
Holly from LSU um Kamari Ramsey from USC
has some fans uh but I think those two
guys the men and Warren probably the
best chance to become starters, which
I I I think I think safety it kind of
gets undervalued when we do like the
contract stuff and we do the um uh the
draft stuff because when you when it
comes down to it, these are guys that
are huge huge contributors in in today's
game. Uh, and obviously like the roles
are going to shift a little bit going
from McDermott to Leonard, but still um
we know uh Leonard going from his time
with the Jets, how big of a role he had
with Rex, and that's obviously a big big
influence on on his defense now. So
maybe they pick one, but I I would say
you got to take one of those two if you
if you're aiming to get a starter in
this draft.
>> Last one for me, Charles, and you
touched on this earlier, the fact that
once again, we have a der of round one
grades in this class. There's probably
only six to eight true blue chippers,
maybe 12 to 15 with true first round
grades. And the Bills, once again, are
at the bottom of round one. So,
how likely do you think it might be that
the Bills could just move out of round
one alto together, especially knowing
they don't have a second round pick
after the DJ Moore trade?
>> Yeah, I I think that makes a lot of
sense. Um, you know, I I I still, you
know, I still think there's room for for
like to consider, you know, even just
adding, you know, another, you know,
maybe even the defensive tackle body. I
know that that Deion Walker uh played
well. I love watching that Kentucky. He
had a nice spurt to the end of the
season. Uh, but there's some interesting
guys like at the that that I like a lot
that could possibly be on the board
there at 26 like Caleb Banks from
Florida that he is like my muse this
year and he's only played three games
and he might be the worst tackler I've
ever seen but he's 66 330 and but and
and like I like he it it's crazy because
he's he's one of those guys he's 66 330
and he's like spinning against double
teams, you know, his his technique is
perfect like he's eating blocks, he's
got good balance, and then he he gets to
the point where he has to make a tackle
and it turns into like an info
commercial or infomercial where, you
know, the guy's like spilling down with
like a bucket of hoses and stuff down
the stairs like, "Why are you doing
that, man? Just
>> just fall on him." Um, but I I I think
it'll be interesting to see like what
what gets valued as terms like traits in
this class because u like someone like
Caleb Banks has a whole lot of athletic
ability. You can kind of see it coming
together, but the production isn't
there. someone like Peter Woods from
Clemson, defensive tackle, falls in the
same spot. But those are guys where it's
like if if we if we can fix him, we
might really have something here. And
>> that's where coaching takes over,
>> you know. Exactly. No, because I I used
to, you know, back in my heyday as a a
Baltimore County uh defensive line coach
uh in Maryland, you know, I I started
watching these guys. I'm like, man, we
can teach them how to tackle. I don't
know. I can't teach 66 330 that can that
can cut on the dime and spin backwards
against the run and keep his leverage,
but we might be able to teach them how
to tackle. And that's where it's going
to be interesting with this with this
class cuz there's a lot of guys that got
good traits that you know you could you
could knock for several reasons, but
someone's got to go in these picks. So,
we'll see what happens.
>> Who's uh who's your surprise pick of
this draft? Do you have a guy that um
either is going to be in the Hall of
Fame after getting passed over by
everybody six times or uh what who what
guy do you has caught your eye that you
think has is going to continue to be
undervalued, but you really think at
some point he's going to be a good pro?
>> Oh, under undervalued. I I was going to
say my guy uh um Monroe Freeling from
Georgia because I like last year after
they lost to Notre Dame, I was like this
guy should not be anywhere near an SEC
football field again in his life and by
the end of this season, he was probably
the best player on offense.
>> You're talking about him being a top 10
pick now.
>> Right. Right. Right. So, but Right. So,
I'm not going to pick him, but I will
I'll I'll give you two people. Uh Max
Achenor from Arizona State. He is an
offensive tackle.
>> Uh he's 66 330 big athlete.
>> He's he's he's got he's got an entry
story because he's a red shirt senior.
>> Uh so he's a little bit older coming
into his draft, but he didn't start
playing football until Jo
uh you know probably you know four or
five years ago. So his first football
experience was Jo. And he didn't quit
which is really amazing. Uh cuz I I
can't imagine walking into Jo football
and that's my first football experience.
Like you're you're built a little bit
different, bro. So, uh he's made a he's
made a lot of progress. And if you watch
his game against David Bailey uh this
past year, Arizona State versus Texas
Tech. Actually, you know, held his own
against David Bailey for for a good
amount of that game. But a deep cut
uh player that I I like this year and I
I know him a lot higher on than most
people is Garrett Nusmire from LSU.
>> Okay.
>> Uh I had him at 28 on my big board. I I
I think when he's healthy,
>> you you can you can see a starting
quarterback there. Um and it kind of
like popped to my brain when I was
watching the Senior Bowl and he he was
the best quarterback on the field, you
know, ripping through the throws. And I
know it's it's sanitized. It's a spring,
it's a, you know, senior bowl game, but
maybe go back and like, oh yeah, he was
hurt for a good chunk of last year. And
when you go back to the healthy games,
like he still looked like someone who
could who could be a first round pick. I
I like his peaks a little bit more than
Tai Simpson. Um, I don't know if he'll
go in the first round, but Garrett
Nusmire, I think he could be a starter
at some point in the near future.
>> Coach's son, too, right? I think he's a
>> coach's son, dog. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. There you go.
>> Interesting. Charles, thanks for the
time as always. We'll catch up with you
down the line as we get closer to the
draft. Thanks for the time today.
>> Yes, sir.
>> I appreciate